Good afternoon, ladies and gentlemen.
我係ethnically Nepalese and born in Hong Kong.
Yet the education system persists to hinder our growth.
pursuing a double major in comparative literature and gender studies.
香港是 my home， like many other ethnic minorities who reside here.
my name is Biddya Shrestha and I'm currently studying in the University of Hong Kong.
今天，我係度address the issue of racial segregation，which occurs within the schools in Hong Kong, which strips away our inherent right to learn Chinese.
好，may we first invite Ms. Kausandip, please. Oh, she's not here, right? Okay, Ms. Bittar Sureshwar, please.
但係，係真係真？
當我 tell  people  that  I  was  born  and  raised  in  Hong  Kong.
The first question that comes up is， how come you don't know Chinese then？
some even simply say that we are lazy and that we never bothered to learn Chinese.
首先，有係一個清晰的分隔，在學校，作為ethnic minorities，係被分隔開同中國學生，自小學一級開始。
因為 Chinese係 so 鑽切 for us in order to survive in Hong Kong, in order to find a job in Hong Kong. This is how important the language is.
我會強調，我們需要的是融合，而不是隔離。我們需要的是與當地的中國學生融合，為了練習中文，為了學得更好中文。
我 come from a local English medium DSS school， and I have witnessed this all my life， where ethnic minorities would have Chinese as second language courses， whereas our Chinese classmates would have serious core subject of Chinese lessons。
唱嘅。
咁第三個嘢咧，就係講緊。
我係活生生的例子，證明我們作為少數民族，仍然在為學中文而苦惱。
啲共用嘅嘢，其實佢係好開心。佢係你善用緊佢之餘，其實其他一啲學生都係學緊一啲佢哋嘅嘢。我覺得呢樣嘢係。
我 acknowledge and greatly appreciate the fact that the government has given us a lot of funds to EM schools. However, how effective are these funds in enabling us to learn Chinese?
我希望我們被允許繁榮、 enrich and to contribute to Hong Kong, which we call our home. Thank you. Thank you, Miss Rester. 哎，跟住又嚟請黃樂容女士嘅唔該。
它多樣文化，和這是我們需要 embracе。一次 again，我會 remind 你，我們需要的是 integration 而不是 segregation。我們是香港的兒童，我們是少數族裔，但我們不是劣等。
好點都好，但係即係完全就冇一個考慮嘅點係話啊，非華裔我就要去啦，即係冇呢個嘢。咁但係啲老師就好自然就會哦，你去呢度啦噉樣。咁其實呢個係意味緊華裔同非華裔嘅學生係分隔咗，即係噉你永遠就喺呢度啦，你哋喺呢度啦噉樣。
At the same time, I believe that there has to be more assistance given to our Chinese brothers and sisters in learning English as well. I believe that for the prosperity of Hong Kong and the harmony of Hong Kong, it is essential that both Chinese and non-Chinese people can communicate with one another, and this is the uniqueness of Hong Kong.
誒，我係三個巴基斯坦籍小朋友嘅補習老師啦，咁都差唔多兩年啦。噉就係小一啦、小四啦同埋小六啦噉樣。咁咧咁主要照顧佢哋啊。誒，處理學校家頭細務嗰個媽媽咧就唔識中文，唔識英文嘅。噉我身上面著緊呢件衫咧。
其實就係小朋友嘅媽媽整畀我嘅，咁即係唔係華華語、華華瑞啊？呢啲其實關係咧，佢哋都係咁努力、咁温暖噉樣去建立嘅。噉我第一樣嘢要講嘅咧，就係普通話教中文嘅差啦，因為咧佢而家個小朋友佢哋冇咗中文。
堂一啲咁正統啦，好針對唯一學廣東話嘅機會咧。咁其實佢哋試過即係課室啊，就明嘅書就唔明啦。咁但係佢哋默書咧就係用普通話㗎嘛，噉就冇咗啦。咁然之後其他科即係可能常識啊、數學啊呢啲都係用。
用翻廣東話嗰啲科咧，噉佢又係完全就係啲文字題，就係啊，完全睇唔明啊，又教佢嘅時候都唔會聽得好明啦。咁第二個嘢咧就係小學同埋中學接駁個問題。噉我而家教緊個小朋友係小六啦，咁即係要升中啦。噉佢有同我講咗好多想。
我想入體藝啊！我想學體育啊！咩噉樣噉，但係咧，佢學校嗰個老師好自然噉就同佢講，就話：啊，你哋入呢間啦，呢啲好多你哋呢啲人嘅學校啊噉樣啦。咁但係小朋友本身就冇諗過啊，華唔華裔或者咩嘅學校，佢就係想啊，我想學呢樣嘢，我睇呢啲banding又。
我哋根本就冇一啲推動誒華裔，即係本地生同埋非華裔生互相嘅教育同埋學習啦。因為噉，我學校誒我小朋友個學校，我覺得都幾好。有一個嘢咧都可以學下，就係有一個環節畀我小朋友上台介紹板球啊，即係。
佢就話啊點樣打啦啊烏都要點樣講加油啦呢啲噉佢咧嗰陣時就好得戚啦，好冷靜噉樣叫我同佢一齊練嗰個稿啦。噉佢就非常之開心，都係咁叫我教佢啊點樣講點樣講。即係噉，其實你好睇到呢啲，只係即係好善用佢哋啲優點，佢哋畀佢哋去誒做呢啲。
係。
多謝，Mr. Remmel。
We now invite Ms Nimbra Khan, please.
Okay，唔該曬，我哋先。May we now invite Miss Christine Romero，please？
Despite this, the government has not done enough to encourage intercultural interactions, sort of like what Miss Wong has mentioned.
共融就係你你要了解我，都要了解你嘅一個過程啦。所以其實呢個雙向溝通咧，我覺得係要需要有。
Between two groups creates resistance towards learning the target language. In that sense, depriving EMs of these intercultural interactions is detrimental to their acquisition of Chinese. Most of the EMs I know who have successfully become fluent in Cantonese tend to have had positive experiences with native speakers at an earlier age than their peers.
Good afternoon, Chairman and government officials. I'm Christine Romero, a Filipino born and raised in Hong Kong, who has completed the HKCEs, the HKA levels and a BA in Language and Communication at Centennial College. I'm also a committee member for Section Juan, a support group for Filipino youths in the city. The issue I'd like to bring forward concerns the government's lack
考慮EM社會環境及語言學習和習得。目前，許多政府的努力都集中在量身訂製NCS課程、提供專業發展及支援教師和學生，以及改善其他學術領域。這有道理。然而，社會和文化互動的重要性。
Second language acquisition has been substantiated by academia for decades. Evelyn Hatt famously wrote about this in 1978. One learns how to do conversation. One learns how to interact verbally, and out of interaction, syntactic structures are developed, which resonates with how I have learned most of my Cantonese.
worse yet the segregation continues to exist in many schools in the city ranging from preschool to secondary we still see Chinese speaking students separated from NCS students the effects of this are twofold firstly it decreases the opportunities for NCS students to gain experience in using the language with native speaking peers currently many NCS students
Are limited to practising in controlled classroom settings that don't always reflect real-life interactions. Considering that many of us have a NCS background, have more fellow NCS than local Chinese in our social circles, many are unlikely to get the practice they need. Successful instructed language learning requires opportunities for output, where students are able
能取得建設性的反饋，某樣東西比從朋友那邊得到的更好，而不是從生氣的校巴司機那邊得到的。第二，分隔減少NCS學生學習語言的動機，因為不同的文化被給予很少機會互動，一種「我們對他們」的思維發展。根據社會心理學，創造社會距離。
Considering the importance of encouraging intercultural interactions in second language learning, we would like to request the government to look beyond academics when forming policies to prevent segregation within the schooling system. All schools should be equipped with skills and resources for teaching CSL. Additionally, the government should enforce against the in-school segregation and give recognition.
到學校，促進和諧的融合。在較大的規模上，我們需要慶祝存在於這座城市中的多樣性，透過公眾教育或甚至市區的節慶活動，來增加對不同文化的欣賞。由於香港本來就是一個國際城市，我相信沒有理由讓我們繼續以如此緩慢的速度進行融合。
Thank you, Chairman. Good evening. My name is Khan Imrabi. I'm a Form Five student and I'm Pakistani and born in Hong Kong. I'm going to pinpoint three issues. Firstly, the small ratio is directly affecting the communication of ethnic minority students. As there are a few Chinese in ethnic minority schools, it will be difficult for ethnic minority.
這些易級別可能會幫我們一段時間，但不是長遠。
我會想明確表示，提供我們更易學的中文課程並不是一個有效的方法來改善我們的中文流利度。
The Education Bureau doesn't feel a need to change because there's a lack of ethnic minorities' voices in Hong Kong to pressure the Education Bureau.
Local primary, kindergarten and secondary schools are written in Chinese, which is difficult for parents to read. This is my speech. Thank you, Ms. Chan. Next, we have Ms. Yunus Nebra, please.
However, second generation or third generation families are now taking every chance to improve their their children's Chinese abilities. For example, many ethnic minorities are trying to speak Chinese more frequently at home.
In our school, can choose which Chinese level they want to learn. And moreover, learning shouldn't be based on teachers' expectations only, but also enable students to have adequate Chinese skills for integration after graduation.
us senior secondary students are taught Chinese topics which are taught to local primary two or three students, which is totally unacceptable. Are we really expected to get a job with the Chinese ability of a local primary student?
語言障礙，between the ethnic minorities and the teachers have always been problematic. On top of that, limited academic assistance from ethnic minority parents make it makes it almost impossible for us to learn Chinese without the support at home.
ethnic minorities are doing their best to integrate to the local committee and its people. Unfortunately, the education bureau still might not be doing enough for us ethnic minorities, which really makes it questionable whether us ethnic minorities are truly considered as true Hong Kongers or not.
Students to learn Chinese fast and communicate in Chinese with Chinese students to practice their speaking instead of learning and reading through from a book. It may also be difficult for ethnic minority students to make friends with Chinese and become sociable with Chinese people, as there are a few number of Chinese in ethnic minority schools. Ethnic minorities students will.
make friends with other ethnic minority students, resulting difficulty in being sociable with Chinese people, which may affect their future. As in their workplace, the number of Chinese people will be more than ethnic minorities people. It will be difficult for ethnic minority students to adapt to the working environment and their workplace. Therefore, with this kind of learning environment, we are
Being racially segregated, it does not help integration for us in the long term, both in language and language learning and social integration. Secondly, most ethnic minority schools won't provide traditional Chinese at their school. Instead, the schools will only provide only easiest Chinese subject level to their students, in which the students.
will learn Chinese as their as the primary primary school students, which can adversely affect their future. If the ethnic minority students choose to stay in Hong Kong and work in Hong Kong, it will be difficult for them to seek jobs in Hong Kong. For example, in my school, there are three levels of learning Chinese: the easiest level, medium level, and difficult level. The students
lastly, some kindergartens and primary schools' website is only available in Chinese, which result in difficult for parents to read. Therefore, the number of kindergartens and primary school is limited to ethnic minority students, as the as their parents can't read the preschool quality reports in some local kindergartens and primary schools. Moreover, the notice provided in
Thank you, Chairman. Good evening. I'm Nebray Unis, currently a secondary five student. I'm a Hong Kong-born Pakistani, and growing up in a community filled with Chinese people was really difficult due to different problems I faced. One of them being discrimination, of course. But discrimination was not the biggest factor hindering my personal growth as an ethnic minority in Hong Kong. Instead, it was the difficulty.
I faced in learning Chinese as it's not my first language. Regarding the education issues I faced, but regarding the education issues faced by ethnic minorities in Hong Kong, I'm specifically going to talk about the problems brought up by the current Chinese curriculum provided to us ethnic minorities. First of all, language
There is no system to teach.
Please provide teaching in mixed teams.
There was not proper training to teach us Chinese as our second language.
教師訓練和教學材料，所以。
Proof as well as their English. From the beginning, the schools give us up to up on us.
教育， to teach non-Chinese speaking students, which could help their Chinese upgrade the same level as Chinese students.
most of us start learning Chinese from kindergarten, but why after fifteen years of education, most of us can only reach a primary through three levels?
Furthermore, having a weak Chinese ability limits our job choices, as many of the jobs require a Chinese requirement of Chinese fluency.
年輕年齡 ensures different races are recognised, accepted and respected in the long run. The governments should establish a diversified policies for schools to integrate ethnic minorities into mainstream classrooms. Leveling the playing field for both Chinese and ethnic minorities would be a great start.
Communication and City University. Today, I'm here to talk about an issue of teachers in ethnic minority EM schools and problems students are facing after graduating from secondary schools. Studying in an EM school myself, I found primary school teachers would teach us basic Chinese, where we learn how to read and write some basic leaflets and poems.
We simply want equal opportunities in Chinese learning, and I don't think the current Chinese curriculum we have provided is effective enough. The curriculum should be suitable enough for us ethnic minorities. Chinese students lack sensitivity towards different races and cultures. Personally, I think that a diverse learning environment at
好教育不是要給每個孩子一樣的幫助，不管他們需要不需要，而是要分配資源給他們需要的地方。謝謝。謝謝，Ms Neuber。我們現在請Ms Zafreen Mavish上台。謝謝。下午好，我叫Mavish Zafreen，我是巴基斯坦人，現在在香港讀英文。
但once I reach secondary school, my Chinese starts to break down. There, literally everything we learned in primary school was being repeated in our secondary school. It was super easy to pass Chinese. It was not helpful at all. The school teachers tried their best to teach us Chinese, but it was never enough for us to improve our language. I believe it's not teachers' fault.
As the language from basic to advanced level, it's just repeated itself. Usually schools assumes we will not know Chinese because it's very hard for us. But in fact neither Chinese nor English is our first language. So how can school assumes our English is better than our Chinese? If we are treated same way as local students, then our Chinese would be improved.
give up on us. They separate Chinese and non-Chinese students in different classes, which is unfair and not equal. We would, why would school do that? Is separating non-Chinese students from local students, our teaching, our simple Chinese, is benefit to us? Is that the right way for us to?
treated like this because we are going to be the part of Hong Kong society in the future. Later, we have this GCSE Chinese after passing the school exam. The certificate does not hold much value itself. It is not good measure to just lower Chinese requirements for EM students because our mother tongue is not Chinese. In order to improve
會教育 bureau 考慮列出所有英語。
The Chinese level teach so students that would not be too different across the schools.
medium of instruction schools under the appendix three or all the schools with experiencing experience in enrolling NCS students for parents' reference.
教育 bureaux 應該提供信息，包括列出學校，誰已經接受 NCS 學生，和他們提供的支援，父母。
English as a medium of instruction, education bureau should not intentionally or unintentionally encourage students to enrol in former designated schools.
Chinese second language need to teach from very beginning to the end. All EM schools should follow same or not same, so they could improve it as needed. Thirdly, without Chinese DSE, it's impossible for
它應該不責備決定修改 primary one 採取入學分配安排的某些 NCS 父母。它是在誤導公眾認為入讀傳統上收納非中文母語學生的學校是父母的選擇。
和機會去旁邊中國學生，如果教育局認為要照顧不能用中文作為學習媒介的學生，是要給他們更多學校選擇，那麼附錄三應該列出所有使用。
EDB could provide schools teachers guideline booklets that could be used to teach EM students. A manual should be provided to all teachers teaching them step to step teaching as has a second language by introducing them the culture different background things to be aware of knowing second language Chinese.
aim to reach higher posts in some fields because their requirements required Chinese DSE level. Mostly, into ships of university is coming in Chinese catalogue. Thank you. Thank you, Miss Murphy. Next, could we have Miss Peo Beswos, please? Thank you, Mr. Chairman. Today, I want to talk about the prevailing primary.
一 admission system，所以這就是實際上現在的表格，用於小一的錄取。如果你看第七欄，也就是用紅圈圈起來的，這是一個讓家長填寫的方格，裡面寫著「不能用中文作為學習媒介」。
所以如果我係一個家長，如果我check呢個方框，我會被指派到附錄三的這八間學校。這八間學校其實係主要傳統上接受更多非中文母語學生的學校。在2006年，公營教育委員會
公開聽證會，幾組及族裔少數羣體的家長出席會議時，並非最關心的是他們能否在NCS學校就讀，而是學校的教學語言是否適合NCS學習。因為推行母語政策，許多學校使用中。
Chinese as the teaching medium. Schools teaching English as MoI is limited in number. The then education secretary, Miss Fanny Law, had said to open more English schools for NCS will not help them integrate in society. So that's why the former designated schools became the only option for people.
多謝。我們現在有Ms. Bibi Miriam，請。
同埋標準咧，可以幫助去提升學生嘅中文學習能力啦，同埋可以建立更好嘅中文學習基礎。唔該曬。
教育局似乎間接鼓勵父母，鼓勵 racial 分隔，所以 EDB 會做啲嘢嚟打消呢個印象同公眾嘅擔憂。多謝主席。
公眾同埋家長啊，都唔知道政府會向學校提供呢啲資金。即管你去話教育局每年都會花兩億去支持非華裔學生去學中文，但係政策仲未夠具體。
who want to learn English, who want to use English as a learning medium. In fact, Hong Kong Unison's research in 2015 on parental choice in primary school selection show that ethnic minority parents do not tend to choose racially segregated schools for their children. Can EDB clarify who are they referring to as?
不同 stakeholders， where do these stakeholders express their opinion and what are their actual worries? When parents say that their children cannot use Chinese as learning medium, they want to find schools which use English as learning medium, but not to enrol in schools with more non-Chinese speaking students and lose the Chinese learning environment.
大家好，我叫黛雅，我係一個萬誒香港出世嘅孟加拉人，我依家喺城市大學讀緊書，我今日會講關於中國語文第二語言學習架構嘅資助啦。雖然行政長官喺一四年嘅施政報告中宣造宣佈咗去實施呢箇中國語文課程第二語言嘅架構啦。
即係CSL，畀啲少數族裔學生去學好中文啦。但係呢啲措施係唔足夠嘅，點解咧？因為缺乏咗具體嘅課程啦、基準啦、教材啦、教師培訓啦、評估啊，同埋誒監督機制等嘅關鍵細節。此外，教育局係冇做足夠嘅諮詢，政府喺一四年至一五年。
花咗一點九億去加強非華語學生對中文嘅知識，但呢啲活動嘅進展係唔明確嘅。而且呢種資助係咪真係為能夠為少數族裔帶來益處，同埋教育政策上係咪誒有效改善佢哋嘅語文能力咧？呢個就好值得去探討。而家好多公
對學校嘅支持係應該要明確嘅，應該要有個透明度喺度。點樣去做到呢樣嘢？就係應該去建立一個績效指標。依家學校嘅課程係咪有一個教學嘅目標咧？我覺得未夠清楚，噉就證明咗有個不足之處。同埋老師好難喺一個得唔到相關培訓嘅情況之下。
去制定一個適合嘅課程畀非華裔學生。其實除咗學校嘅自我報告之外，我哋應該利用其他評估工具，例如學生嘅意見啦、佢哋對課程嘅瞭解啦同埋睇法。我就覺得有幾個解決方案。第一就係我哋應該去深究老師嘅師資同埋對課程系統作出相。
相關嘅改善，同埋我哋應該有個階段學習嘅目標，建立成果指標同埋審核計機制。更加重要嘅係，我哋應該要有專業嘅老師培訓，為學校提供專業嘅支持，提供更多嘅教學計劃同埋資源。最後，將少數族裔納入香港嘅主流學校。等佢。
Next, we have Miss Nambiar Raman, please.
取得他們學位，仍無工作，因為他們的中文能力低。
There are many youths like me, despite having gone through the local education system, who are who have the ability to speak the language, but do not have the ability to read or write Cantonese fluently.
The content taught in school is frankly too easy and too repetitive. I mean, imagine studying Cantonese for 15 years and only being able to say 啊，孫何志，啊，孫世玉，丹，丹高。
my language ability is low, not because I am lazy or that my parents do not wish for me to learn the language, but it is the issue of not having progressive Chinese language curriculum in schools, and this is what I would like to bring forth in today's hearing.
And I was the general secretary at Amnesty International Club at HKU. I don't say this to sound arrogant or cocky. I say this because even someone like me cannot make it in the system. Why, you ask? Because my ability to speak Cantonese is comparable to that of a primary student.
要結論，代替只給我們選擇較易中文學習的選項，在長遠，解決方案應該是發展一個更好的中文課程，為閩南語學生，所以即使我們母語不是中文，我們仍可以學到中文至一個水平，作為一個本地學生，就像中文學生學英語一樣。謝謝。
佢哋有翻個歸屬感，同埋可以同本地人溝通多啲。咁試問政府建立咗呢樣呢個架構已經四年啦，咁可唔可以同我哋講翻，其實有幾多學生係可以已經係考中國語文嘅文憑試去取取得呢個等級咧？我哋係咪可以有呢個統計嘅數據咧？咁績效指標同。
主席，我係Mary Beebee，目前讀第二年學年，讀心理學係，於港大讀書。我係香港出生長大，我讀幼稚園到現在讀大學，都係讀香港大學。我想講嘅係，大學入學要求，用中文寫，唔係偏袒少數民族。大家都知道，即使係。
Even though non-Chinese-speaking students are exempt from taking the DSE Chinese, but are required to take alternative Chinese such as GCAL, GCAS, GCSE, IGCSE or HKDSE Applied Learning Chinese in order to replace DSE Chinese language to meet the minimum entrance requirement. There are a few issues I would like to mention.
首先，no matter one gets grade A10 in applied Chinese or grade C in GCSE or even grade A in GCIAL， you will be granted level three. Even though this helps to fulfil the Chinese requirement， but it does not give any recognition to harder Chinese level. Referring to the grading system of the Chinese.
Chinese language. It seems like there seem to be no point of choosing a higher level of Chinese requirement if the point is going to be level three. And secondly, there seem to be no way of calculating the Chinese language for ethnic minorities. Even though said by the universities, the Chinese language for ethnic minorities will be counted as.
Level three, but no university seems to admit that when asked, and we are always told that each of the ethnic minorities' Chinese language will be calculated case by case. I can recall something similar that happened to me in 2016 on my DSE result day. I called some of the universities to find out how they calculate the Chinese language of ethnic minorities.
On some of the courses I wanted to study, however, none of the universities were able to give me a clear answer. Some said it will be counted as level two. Some said it will be counted as level three. Others said it will be counted at case by case. And this actually disfavours ethnic minorities as they do not have any guidelines on how to calculate their Chinese language and their total DSE score.
this gives them fewer chances to choose the right course from themselves. As a result, this does not only add difficulties to us when we are doing the DuPont marks calculation, but also discourages students from studying a harder Chinese level. As a short-term solution, I would like to request for giving higher recognition to harder Chinese level, recognising our Chinese ability.
According to the levels and a clear calculating method for grading alternative Chinese language should be provided by all institutions in Hong Kong. Moreover, waiving our Chinese requirement is not a benefit to us, but a remedial measure for the lack of proper Chinese as a second language curriculum from the government. We want to learn Chinese.
但問題不是我們工作努力不努力，而是老師和學校是否準備教我們達到那水平。每個人都質疑孩子學習中文作為第二語言的能力，但沒有人質疑老師的教學經驗和培訓，關於教中文作為第二語言。這就是為什麼即使今天，這仍然是一個巨大的問題。
Good evening, Chairman and committee members. I am Raman Lamia Shreya. I am a Bangladeshi born and raised in Hong Kong. I studied in ethnic minority school. I am currently a year three student at the University of Hong Kong. I am a chairperson of Equal Opportunity Student Ambassador. I am a fellow of the foundation called Resolve.
多謝，Miss Lenzien。
I mean, we now have Miss Farah Bakar, please.
謝謝你，所以多謝你嘅時間。謝謝，Ms. Moran。
係 progressive and again not repetitive.
所以，我的老師 said 詞，like 你哋 doomed to fail， or 你會 just end up as a waiter。
There is no point in putting so much resources if they are not going to yield the desired results.
other than that, most of our parents do not even know that they enrol their children in schools who do not even care about our individual development.
Can't pass as locals because we learn very basic Cantonese, whereas native English speakers because we have teachers who can't even properly communicate in English.
of teachers, especially to take effort to train cultural understanding, so that our teachers will be free from stereotypes. Thank you.
Many of the ethnic minorities have been living here for generations and are still not fluent in Cantonese, and this shows that the policy of Chinese as a second language is a utter failure.
already have preconceived stereotypes in E.M. schools. I recall when I was in Form Four, I was placed in a class deemed as the second worst class. One day, some of my classmates were unable to do their homework.
We need a platform where university students can bridge the gap in their level of Cantonese, because even when we want to further studies, many courses require us to have high fluency in Cantonese.
他們甚至不知道什麼是HKDSE。存在著溝通不足的問題。父母和老師之間，對個別學生的評論被老師們一般化，因為他們只關注10名學生，這些學生被老師認為有機會進入大學。
although the education bureau has allowed non-Chinese students to have alternative Chinese qualifications such as GCE, GCE and IGCSE, it cannot be denied that that level attained cannot match the standards needed for workplace. Therefore, it is not uncommon to hear that some of the graduates who have
在大學和機構，ethnic minority學生也無法彌補中文的差距，因為沒有中間地帶讓ethnic minority學生學習進步的中文，因為提供的課程是給初學者或已經參加DSE的進階學生。
我們 acknowledge that the Education Bureau has implemented various support measures, but through this platform today, we are urging for a holistic development within the Chinese educational framework, and that means first we need the content of the Chinese courses to be administered and evaluated to ensure that they.
We now have Miss Denzel Lenzion, please. Thank you. My name is Denzel, a Filipina graduate from Dalia Memorial School, and a current student at the University of Hong Kong. People, well, parents per se assume that teachers who are in schools that are concentrated in EM students would be expert and culturally aware with teaching.
The truth is, it's not. Teachers in concentrated EM schools lack teacher training, which therefore makes them incapable of teaching us. Because of that, they are ignorant to the fact that they could not teach us. Rather, they automatically perceive that we are not capable of furthering our education here in Hong Kong. Here, you can see that teachers.
therefore。
特別是到EM學生。
Chinese會 definitely improve through the funding.
Next, we have Ms. Omi Aslam, please.
just a gentle reminder, the microphones are very sensitive. You don't have to speak too close to them.
Now，I have a sister who's currently studying in an in a Chinese primary school.
都係用中文授課，例如數學和普通科。
這項應該做，為確保撥款能有效地及高效地由學校利用。
政府和EDB has failed to do anything to ensure racial equality in the education sector.
Good evening. My name is Habiba, and I'm a student of City University of Hong Kong. I was born and raised in Hong Kong, and I'm able to speak fluent Cantonese.
Although she is struggling with learning Chinese, she is very much interested and enjoys learning Chinese. However, with the support of Chinese learning, I'm sure.
兩者政府和EDB都強調強調提供均等服務給所有層級，但是否真的均等，是個問題。
今天，我會講述關於由教育局撥款給本地小學及中學，以支援非中文母語學生學習中文的問題。
We're already marginalised in society and even in our schools. That's ridiculous. We're fed by those thoughts and because that, we're demotivated by our own teachers. Ironically, moreover, the kind of educational environment that we that we receive in these schools when we graduate, it worsens our adaptation here in Hong Kong. We can't.
但 parents so do not know this because schools are starting to become a marketing tool to promote their greatness but does not deliver. Also, I think it's the EDB's job to take efforts to inform EM parents about the education system here in Hong Kong and should make it compulsory for schools to provide information on the qualification.
Now, the education fund for non-Chinese speaking students must be used by schools to help them with Chinese learning. EDB should ensure that schools have applied for the fund and it's being justly used for the students. Because without the support through the funding, students do not only do poorly in Chinese subjects, but also other subjects.
現在，雖然EDB有監察機制來確保學校在使用撥款支援NCE學生，但措施被錯誤實施，沒有明顯的改變可見於EM學生。應該增加透明度和對公眾的責任。
學校應該報報給EDB和公眾，透過財務報告，這應該包括如何使用撥款。例如，學校應該提供額外的中文課後或在週六，他們可以聘請中文教師專門教NC學生，因為全職正規教師可能沒有足夠時間。
alot a lot of it is due to their perception.
他們可以提供額外資源，來增強中文學習。
They can measure the funding and the support's effectiveness and the efficiency.
Proactive role in their children's education is quite hard for them and quite worrying.
但最 biggest 問題係 not 只係 about the parents， 但係 discontent  between the schools and the families。
生長在香港，近來所有，和我們想被同等對待，作為本地中國學生。
學校在香港 often 缺 engagement with ethnic minority families in Hong Kong，因為他們不 think 他們 can。
just a little help of funding will change the lives of many people in Hong Kong. Thank you. Thank you, Mr. Islam.
And the main focus I want to talk about today is parents. What can parents do to help fulfil their children's dreams?
The EDB also should arrange bi-annual meetings with the local schools to report, analyse and evaluate the support provided to the students through the funding.
example of this because I went through the designated schools such as Delhi Memorial School, whereas if I believe that if I was placed in a local environment, I would be able to adapt and maybe one day sit among these ethnic minorities and try to help them as well.
They should also evaluate the students' performance before and after support. Now through these measures, the students, the non-Chinese speaking students, will be able to improve their Chinese and will be able to integrate into the society, and will feel like a Hong Konger as well. Because we all were born.
We now have Mr. Shaquille Muhammad, please. Thank you, Chairman. Good evening. My name is Muhammad Shaquille Andres. I I was not born in Hong Kong, but I was definitely raised here. My education here was primarily in a non-Chinese school, so I was from a designated Chinese school. I'm now twenty years old and I'm.
We have Miss Susinda Geron, please.
effective choices for them to nourish their Cantonese ability.
一個進步的課程，我們不能有一個沒有另一個。謝謝。謝謝，Mr. Room。
The school notices are not bilingual, but sometimes it's only in Cantonese. And also in primary school, there's not a lot of.
我係在大學讀政治和公務行政。我嘅夢想係成為一個公務員，像香港嘅人一樣。但不幸嘅係，因為我嘅中文唔夠流利，我唔會實現呢個夢想。但係今日我唔係講我，我係講未來嘅一代。
and also it is due to the perception of the teachers. Teachers perceive that families don't want to be involved in their children's education, when in fact families don't know how to be involved. Parents are not equipped with the necessary information to select suitable schools for their children's growth in Hong Kong. Now I'm an living.
For the parents' perspective, parents are sometimes hesitant to become involved in schools because they don't have the extra time or because they don't speak English nor Cantonese. Some parents work two jobs just to get by for their children, and this and asking parents to have this really.
parents believe that they are not welcome by the schools. The lack of an effective communication channel for parents to acquire information from schools hinders them from selecting a suitable school. So this can be exemplified in when parents try to try to enrol their kids in nursery school when
所以， in essence， I wish that schools in Hong Kong would play a more proactive role in devising communication strategies to convey what is important in a way that can be heard by parents and families and invites them to respond. So it can be a two-way communication. Thank you. Thank you, Mr. Mohamed. Next.
Thank you, Chairman. Good afternoon. I'm Susie Anna Grew, a Nepalese Hongkonger currently studying in the University of Hong Kong. Today, I would like to talk about the issues of teachers within designated schools and how we should offer them guidance and support. Growing up in a designated school system myself, I found that new graduate teachers who came to our school were often
Often underprepared and overwhelmed by the diverse environment presented to them, obviously it is not the teachers' fault. However, we must equip them so that both teachers and students can have a friendly environment. I think it is the education bureau's own responsibility to offer not only guidance but teacher training before the teachers start training. Simply teaching cultural sensitivity.
Universities wouldn't be enough, although we should definitely have teachers taught that, and they should be exposed to a diverse set of learners during their practicum. However, teachers within designated schools often do not have teaching qualifications such as a teaching degree, and they might not even possess a teaching license. Hence, even if we were to provide this form of training within university
For the teaching degree, how can we guarantee people with teaching licences and differences will go to teach in designated schools? Teaching in designated schools wouldn't seem attractive to them, and there's also the issue of the cultural hurdle. Hence, to be more realistic, schools should serve as a connecting point with the help of EDB. So, I would like to offer some suggestions.
EDB應該首先幫助學校創建一個教師指導手冊的模板，這可以由學校進一步編輯，以符合其特定的風格和需求。一本指南書應該提供給所有新教師，教導他們文化敏感性，通過介紹他們到學生的文化、要留意的事項、提供指導和幫助他們適應可能。
文化衝擊。工作坊應該也設置，以進一步培養這些教師，並提供他們實作訓練，關於文化敏感度，因為這不是輕易可取的事，也不是可以在短時間內學會的。這是一個持續進步。另外，教師訓練課程應該是對所有老和新教師都必須的，而不僅僅是選項。第三，
學生的意見應該被收集匿名地，圍繞問題，例如教師語言、對待和教學對他們。每年，我們必須重視我們學生的意見，以改善他們的教育質量。很多族裔少數學生停止注意，甚至從學校退學，因為他們的教師創造一個敵對的環境，説像你永遠。
be as good as a Chinese student at a local school. You won't even be able to enter university. Just focus on passing in class. Things I've heard teachers tell their students, and something I personally heard my teacher say to my class very often when I was in secondary school. How can we expect the students to grow academically if our own teachers think so lowly of them? Teachers are supposed to be our mentors in life.
inside and outside the classroom. But why do they divide us by ethnicity? The summer holiday should also be adequately used to further grow teachers to aid them in issues they encounter by creating a support group to further develop teaching strategies for each subject. The common misconception is that ethnic minority kids are failing or unable to go to university due to their low Chinese ability.
但根據數據，ethnic minor kids are struggling to do well in other subjects as well，such as maths or liberal studies. The teaching quality and guidance has to be provided and improved for more than just Chinese as a second language. It must span all subjects wide. I hope that everyone in Hong Kong can receive quality education regardless of our differences. Teachers are as important as the need for
Next, we have Mr. Ryo Suna, please.
Next, we have Miss Omi Aslam, please.
Anna, global level. Thank you. Thank you, Ms. Aslam.
他 also went to primary school where PMIC was adopted from primary one to primary six.
在一些學校，我們沒有選擇來選擇教學媒介，因為PMIC是完全採用的。
學生， who are majority in the school， and he as the minority is left disadvantaged and on his own.
Thank you, Chairman. Good evening. I'm Salma, ethnically Pakistani, born and raised in Hong Kong, and currently a student studying at HKUST.
他唔做得好喺中學科目，因為佢嘅聽力同綜合技能表現非常差，因為佢嘅聽力同綜合技能表現非常差，因為佢嘅聽力同綜合技能表現非常差，因為佢嘅聽力同綜合技能表現非常差，因為佢嘅聽力同綜合技能表現非常差，因為佢嘅聽力同綜合技能表現非常差，因為佢嘅聽力同綜合技能表現非常差，因為佢嘅聽力同綜合技能表現非常差，因為佢嘅聽力同綜合技能表現非常差，因為佢嘅聽力同綜合技能表現非常差，因為佢嘅聽力同綜合技能表現非常差，因為佢嘅聽力同綜合技能表現非常差，因為佢嘅聽力同綜合技能表現非常差，因為佢嘅聽力同綜合技能表現非常差，因為佢嘅聽力同綜合技能表現非常差，因為佢嘅聽力同綜合技能表現非常差，因為佢嘅聽力同綜合技能表現非常差，因為佢嘅聽力同
我 likes to explain this with the example of my brother, who is in Form Three in a mainstream secondary school, where PMI C is adopted from Form One to Form Three.
To enhance the trilingual ability of the students, but it is based on the assumption that Cantonese is our mother tongue, which is not the case. Our language needs should also be catered for.
在學校，where PMIC is adopted， we already face difficulties learning Chinese， but when it is taught in Putonghua， it further challenges our language ability， especially in listening and integrated skills。
Our multilingual ability shows that we are able to learn and willing to learn. However, there is inadequate support from schools due to the lack of funding from EDB in assisting ethnic minority students when learning Chinese in Putonghua.
我會講到關於使用普通話作為教學媒介語授課的問題。在主流學校，漢語作為中國的官方語言，而中國的語言教育以漢語為主要教學語言。
Putonghua for most ethnic minority students is neither our mother tongue nor is our second or third language. It is in fact our fourth or fifth language after English, our mother tongue, Cantonese, and Arabic for some. I understand that Hong Kong's policy on language education is.
In addition, he is the only EM student in the school who is taking the local Chinese language curriculum. However, he is not given any tailor-made support from the school because resources are being used to implement lessons only for Chinese as a second language students. Chinese as a second language.
我會因此建議EDB撥特別撥款給學校，PMIC正在採用，並給予，無論有多少少數族裔學生，所以他們不會受到不利影響。最終，這些優秀學生將能夠貢獻給香港。
Thank you, Chairman.
only taught simple things.
teaching us Chinese.
影響 us in higher education and our working life.
Why is the Chinese learning not making any real change so far?
simple translation with no further explanation or examples.
few teachers are even unwilling to answer our questions in English.
他們就 assume 我們 understand  what  they are saying, which leads us to lose focus once again.
beginner, medium and hard, and each group feels like they aren't learning more than they already know.
Moreover, the Cantonese classes offered in high diploma is too easy and simply divided into three groups.
I would like to become a music producer. However, how am I supposed to work with basic Cantonese within the field?
And also, why is the new applied learning Cantonese classes only teaching Cantonese to be used in within the service industries?
hence I would like to call for a curriculum that extends to university level. Because what about us who has already graduated from secondary school? The government should set a Chinese level standard for the schools to follow in.
Good evening. My name is Royal Chanar and I'm a Hong Kong citizen currently studying digital music and media at the Hong Kong Design Institute. Today I would like to discuss about the issue of having a unified standard across all schools with ethnic minority students for the Chinese curriculum and how this later.
for me and my classmates, we were always taught the same materials in Chinese class over and over again in secondary school. This made us lose focus when we were younger because it's too easy. Hence, our goal became just to pass in class because no matter what, we are.
Moreover, for myself and other ethnic minorities, students in higher education like high diploma, we are subjected to unfair teaching standards. As even when the classes are supposed to be taught in English, the teacher switches over to Cantonese often and just gives us.
主題。
我們也 deserve  the opportunity to
Why not make us better prepared?
Segregation and promote interaction between these groups of students.
something that they should be responsible to do without without us telling them.
Sometimes the teacher won't even translate until we ask, and they often forget.
It is hard for us as the minority to keep interrupting the class to ask for translation.
Chinese education，especially after two to four years，as we will be heading to the workforce.
Moreover, we would, we must enforce more control among classes in tertiary institutions to be taught in English, if it's advertised to be taught in English.
We pay the same tuition fee as our Chinese classmate, but why do we receive, why do we not receive the same treatment? Thank you. Thank you, Mr. Suna. We now invite Ms. Cindran Angelie, please.
There are also a number of students just like me. In the long run, if we are to stay and work in Hong Kong, we need to have a proficient level of Chinese, especially for our reading and writing skills, as we are always judged by our academic abilities when we look for jobs.
Thank you, Chairman. Good afternoon, everyone. My name is Shashindran Anjali, and I am a second-year student studying Bachelor of Sciences at the Hong Kong University of Science and Technology. I come from an Indian background, and I have been living in Hong Kong since the age of one. I have been studying here since kindergarten all the way to now in second in university.
Therefore, I should be considered as a local Hong Kong student, shouldn't I? But I wish I could say the same thing for my Cantonese proficiency. Now, being able to speak fluent Cantonese really helped me break the language barrier when it comes to talking to local Hong Kongers. Even listening to Cantonese television is not my major problem. What I would
I would like to point out is my literacy level. I have completed the GCSE Chinese in Form 5 and GCSE A S level in Form 6, attaining the highest grade possible. But it is said that this alternative examination is equivalent to a primary school student. So basically, you are saying that my Cantonese is stuck at a primary level.
therefore I would like to suggest some ideas that could help local ethnic minority students, especially the younger generation, to boost their Chinese proficiency, which is comparable to that of a local Chinese student. First, starting from primary school, every student, regardless of ethnicity, should share the same Chinese lesson to alleviate
It may be difficult as EM students, their Chinese is not their first language and they have little exposure to the culture, hence making it hard to follow the learning pace. Even so, instead of having separate classes, I believe bridging programmes and supplementary classes can be provided to these students, just like for others.
incorporate the vast cultures present in our future classrooms.
magnified in the classroom, where contact is necessary but disconnected.
這會 broaden the world as a whole for all students, and enable those in minority to feel more understood deeply.
back in secondary school, because I was placed in the GCSE Chinese curriculum since form one, it was like repeating basic primary level Chinese for another six years.
另一個簡單方式，為政府處理此問題，就是將民族文化融入我們社會，而不是隻注重西方文化與傳統在教科書中。
和中學生，
第二，在中學，EM學生如果在香港完成完小教育，應該有資格修讀中一的中一中文課程，因為最終每個中學生都要參加中一的中一中文考試。
therefore I believe only under certain conditions, just like when a school has newly arrived EM students, or even there are some handful of EM students that fail to meet the DSE Chinese, can be allowed to opt for alternative Chinese. I believe not every EM student should be grouped together and be placed into the alternative.
Chinese curriculum. Then I would like to restate my point that all options for alternative Chinese should not be an immediate option for local EM students with complete primary education in Hong Kong. Finally, I would like to suggest, I would like to ask the EDB whether you have considered revising the DSE Chinese syllabus.
Referring to HKCEE English language, which was comprised of syllabus A and B, I believe DSE Chinese could be separated into an easier and difficult syllabus so that students can have more options within a single syllabus, and this can also meet academic standards for a wide range of students. Both E and
謝謝主席。我的名字是Roy Ireland L， a year three education major student at the University of Hong Kong。香港是個考績重視的城，我們都可以證明。有著強調得高分和優秀DSE考試，以進入大學。然而，即使有99.3%
率 of admission in secondary schools, the number is different for ethnic minorities whose dropout rates are increasingly high, with the number for the Nepalese population being 20.6%, the highest among all the EM population, as reported in the research analysis paper by the University of Hong Kong's Centre for Comparative and Public Law, and
Why is it so? One startling to some, but a no-brainer to others, is the lack of cultural sensitivity highly seen in majority of the city's teachers, especially in the aspect of teaching NCS Chinese. However, the lack of progressive Chinese curriculum isn't the only reason for the high number. The education system itself treats ethnic minority
minority students with a predetermined destiny of failure, causing students to be even to be demotivated before even trying. And here is why: cultural sensitivity is of extreme importance in this day and age, where there is so much diversity in our community, and yet there is a segregation between the locals and the EMs that is.
This is important to note, as it can affect a teacher's ability to teach and the students' ability to learn due to the lack of connection at a culturally responsive level, because their cultures and experiences guide their learning habits, opinions and answers. One thing to note is that it does not mean teachers have to know about each culture.
但rather that they are aware that differences are present and have surface knowledge about the ethnicity that has been in Hong Kong for decades. However, teaching degrees are often missing this as a core. Next year, I'm going to be a teacher in training, and I have yet to see a core course serving to teach and guide us to.
從 now，thank you。thank you，Miss Piani。
一個誒議題啦，就係小學嘅一校一社工。
誒，跟住由你請屯門社區網絡嘅黃德源先生唔該。
And that in itself makes a huge difference for those young souls out there trying to build their own identity, guided by the societal, ethnic and socio-economical experiences that they face. Thank you.
如果政府依家放風出嚟話有機會推行一校一社工嘅話咧，我支持反對，我係反對嘅。但係我反對嘅唔係一校一社工本身，我反對嘅係政府現有嘅一校一社工政策、一校一社工方案。
Thanks, Mr Sharma. Next, we have Ms. Pooja Paryani, please. Thank you, Chairman. Whilst it is commendable that the government has committed a substantial amount of funding to support the rollout of the CSL learning framework, and we do appreciate that measures require time to take hold, the ethnic minority community cannot wait indefinitely for the provision of equal access to quality education.
which is a basic human right for all children. Hong Kong's ethnic minorities suffer in an education system which fails to cater to their linguistic status. How can children who are unable to even enter schools where the learning framework is being implemented benefit from these measures? Where the learning framework is implemented, NCS children remain sidelined by the attitudes of the teachers, as we've just heard.
poor communication between teachers and parents and the prevalence of harmful stereotypes about ethnic minorities and their intellectual competence. This impacts student learning motivation and equal access to opportunities for achieving excellence. Clearly, teacher training needs to address unconscious biases, and this must be made mandatory for all teachers in training. Over the past four years, eight hundred million.
已經有數千萬美元被花在實施中文語言支援措施上，為NCS兒童。然而，這些措施具體是什麼，以及不同學校如何使用，我們並不知道。它們標準化嗎？它們有不同嗎？教師或學校如何確定這些差異化方法的有效性？以及在語言習得方面，結果如何？
簡單包括一兩句話在學校資料中是完全不夠的，從可追蹤的角度，家長們幾乎無法在這個基礎上做出知情的選擇。政府如何能接受這個做法？考慮到涉及的龐大金額，良好的治理需要定期監察、評估和透明度來確定有效性。
當我們已經有廣泛數據，documenting gross inequalities and disadvantages experiences experienced by ethnic minorities across the board，without any information on the effectiveness of the measures，how can we have the confidence that this approach is now going to work to help ethnic minority children？Despite the fact that a research evaluation framework
has been in place since the introduction of the learning framework four years ago. The framework nor its outcomes of evaluation have ever been made public. Pending the release of the comprehensive report on the effectiveness of the CSL learning framework, the EDB is strongly urged to provide a preliminary overview of the findings, updated on an annual basis until such report is released. The EDB is also
也呼籲，要追蹤申請者由NCS學生、其面試率、成功錄取及就讀統計，以及NCS考試表現及畢業率，跨校型別，以釐定通往成功語言及社會融合的途徑。在香港，繪製這些趨勢可幫助識別成功及失敗的因果因素。
不同ethnic groups in various contexts and help inform future strategies for change. Without a data-driven or evidence-based approach, we are just shooting in the dark, relying on a stroke of luck. But our children are not chips for gambling. Generations of ethnic minority children have seen their dreams sacrificed in a broken system. Education is a fundamental multiplier right that opens up.
我們不能允許一個系統繼續存在，這個系統會讓亞裔永遠處於貧窮狀態。我們不能允許這個系統繼續存在，這個系統會讓亞裔永遠處於貧窮狀態。我們不能允許這個系統繼續存在，這個系統會讓亞裔永遠處於貧窮狀態。
係，多謝主席。我係屯門社工網絡發言人黃德源。咁咧就住小族瑞兒童嘅教方式咧，噉我都有少意見想講嘅。咁首先喺共融嗰方面，我覺得有一個職業咧喺誒教育嗰方面，其實可以做到好多嘢，就係社工。咁首先喺最近社會上面討論得非常之烈嘅也。
即切嘅服務去幫到佢哋。
唔少學術研究都話，其實。
你大學嘅中文有啲都係普通話上嘅。
先唔講普通話獨唔獨立成科。
我唔明呢樣嘢究竟對佢哋有咩幫助嘅啫。
價低者得，望落好似好合理，但係事實上如果，
而家我哋身處嘅地方喺香港，唔係喺大陸啊，哥。
跟住最後最後一條問題咧，我係想代我嘅下一代去問嘅。
去做多啲嘢去改善，令到唔同嘅學生真係會有。
小學、中學教普通話，有啲大學咧必修普通話。
呢一個現行嘅制度咧，最令我質疑成效嘅地方就係在於佢嗰個投標嗰個制度。
小學生嗰啲作業，小學生嗰啲功課，小學生嘅測驗考試，你夠膽死畀個繁體字佢，叫佢寫翻個簡體字出嚟？
你一樣嘢我想講嘅咧，就係喺今時今日香港嘅教育制度底下，造就咗少數族裔咧，係唔可以喺社會嗰度向上流，絕對唔可以。
對於學習中文本身有少少困難或者有障礙嘅人咧，你畀兩種嘅文字，你畀兩兩組嘅文字佢啦，一組易，一組難啦。其實佢係會揀容易嗰組嚟學嘅。
對面嘅官員咧，我真係好想問你哋，你知唔知全港有幾多個僱主咧係會請一個完全唔識睇正體字、完全唔識講粵語、淨係識講普通話嘅員工啊？
喺標書上面有好多唔同嘅服務係列曬出嚟嘅話，為咗確保社工要有合理嘅待遇，其實嗰個價錢亦都唔會低得去邊。但係價低者得係咪代表嗰啲學生其實難啲會有一啲好嘅服務咧？咁喺呢個方面咧，我真係好希望政府當局其實可以。
係。
嗯。
Good evening, Mr. Chairman.
各位先生，跟住我哋請Mr. Devan Allen，please。
土生土長嘅香港人會唔會變成少數族裔？
其他學生可以選擇較易的考試路徑。
另一個方式來激勵他們，會是邀請經驗人士來到學校，讓EM學生。
就係香港再繼續面臨咁劣質嘅洗腦教育，咁劣質嘅人口清洗，我哋過咗十年、二十年。
which can help some of the students who are performing well in their overall exams to take a challenge to achieve a higher level of Chinese language skills.
to get this done, we need a lot more motivation and encouragement for both the students and parents, which will be beneficial for their future. It will also make them understand the importance and impact on them mastering the Chinese language for their future lives.
The EDV has taken multiple initiatives in the last few years to integrate the EM with the mainstream community. There are still more steps needed to be taken. As we know, foundation for early education is very important in their higher education and careers. We should explore using different and new initiatives to see which one provides them with the best outcome.
now it is comparatively easier for the EM students to be accepted into tertiary education since universities are accepting different Chinese language exam scores, but it is still very hard and challenging to get into civil service careers where the requirements for the Chinese language standard is very high. So we need a balanced and appropriate curriculum.
Through seminars, they can share their own practical experience on the impact of the Chinese language and what they faced by not knowing the language in a high standard way, and explain what they could achieve if they could master the language. Since some of the parents are found to be not aware of future career paths and education requirements in Hong Kong.
學校或EDB應該組織更多動機講座，為YM家長在早期年紀時，讓他們瞭解如何引導和準備孩子為未來職業和高等教育做好準備。如果家長和學生清楚瞭解不同教育途徑和職業的要件，他們可以做出正確和合適的決定。
As early as possible without wasting their precious time. EDB should also spend more on research as to how they can make the Cantonese learning easier for non-Chinese people. For example, the government can put more investments into making learning Cantonese a more efficient and easier way. Something like app development as part of the curriculum.
Online websites that provide the curriculum and help to do the homework. If possible, some of the study materials can be translated into major EM languages, and if not, just English romanisation would be great help for the parents to engage themselves as well. If some of the EM students opt for extensive Chinese language curriculum based on their interest.
係我有段聲，但係普普通話嘅。
誒我或者我哋將會議延長十五分鐘先，跟住嚟請兩威先生。
一啲額外校內活動。大家唔使諗， former president of Bangladesh Association。 Thank you, Mr. Lam.
1974年是香港警方下屬組織，是對香港青少年進行法治教育和愛國主義教育的重要平台。迄今已累計吸引一百萬名青少年參與，會員超過二十一萬人。
對於一個職業路徑，他們正在夢想的，他們應該被鼓勵和支持，由輔導補助，他們可以被允許自由使用，為他們的中文語言學習。學校行政和教師應該採取有效的措施，為這些學生融入中文學生，為語言實踐，學校內，通過不同的。
誒呢個就啱啱年三十咧，就誒習主席答少年警訊個誒嗰封信嘅何卡嗰個新聞嚟嘅。咁其實咧，大家睇翻啱啱星期日咧，相應北京誒東奧閉幕嗰度咧，嗰幅畫面都係五族共和，後屘五十六個民族出曬嚟㗎。
咁其實咧，誒八十年代嗰陣時咧，就係中國而家係有五十六個民族，咁咧就超過咗好似五千個咧，就先算一個大嘅族項。即係好簡單，女兒國、蘆姑湖嗰啲少數咧，即係未夠五千就唔當一個族。咁誒，台灣嘅高山族咧，即係但但係台灣咧就變咗係九個族嘅台山。
台灣自己計翻，咁但係即係基於我哋香港咧，就係誒即係殖民地留低嘅嘢啦，噉就變咗係誒我哋係有好多誒不同種族嘅人士啦。咁誒其實咧誒兒童權利公約咧第一條咧，大家睇翻咧係我哋其實超曬齡嘅，十八歲留下。
啊！嚇，噉我哋就已經超過十八歲嘅。咁今日亦都發生一件事咧，就係第二條嗰所講，小朋友應該係有自己表達嘅能力。噉啊，希望教育局咧，即係盡快就係即係開學咧，將呢個信息話畀小朋友聽。即係其實點講，不論任何種族都好，小朋友有生存權嚇。
咁即係好簡單，就誒曾經試過阿翁正晶律師都講話佢阿劉師傅走嘅時候咧，佢好激動，係佢個女叫翻我唔走啊。即係你要傳遞呢個意識畀佢哋啲小朋友自己知道，因為呢樣嘢係好重要嘅，因為佢淨係follow父母。即係好簡單，我睇到今日少數族裔即係上半場。
場好似得一個小朋友啫，噉就亦都奇怪。今日本來係兒童事務委員會成立，上晝突然間成個會抽起咗，我都唔知點解啦嚇。咁誒，我上次喺兒童誒事務委員會提過啦，其實咧誒，我去瑞士阿伯恩，即係啱啱啊特首上個月都去過瑞士，即係大巡會啦。我希望就係話。
要畀少數族裔，即係其實瑞士嗰個以誒有四種language嘅法語、德語、意大文，同埋誒佢本身誒瑞士一種話係四個議員。新加坡係四個啦，咁即係其實嚟講咧，你要有人物係代表去講嘢，同埋佢自己知點解我提提少年警訊咧？其實少年警訊誒。
七十年代幾好嘅佢暑期咧，佢有啲日營咧，即係變咗。有啲小數族裔咧，喺度study學嘢。即係譬如而家啊，啱啱睇啱啱睇到新春團拜啊。梁家榮講就係教育電視，教育電視就係已經有四十年啦。咁唔好三廿二台成日播河口湖同埋播誒簡普寨噉。
你每一日有個channel係每一種小數族類嘅語言，等佢睇咗嚟學啦。唔該曬咁多位。唔該，威先生。誒，局長就第二節發有冇咩回應？好啊，多謝主席。咁咧，就住剛才咧誒好多位誒嘅代表咧，大家都誒關注嘅問題咧，我想誒誒重點講一講。噉啊，我見到咧呢一個。
同學咧係畀學生同埋家長係有得選擇嘅。多謝主席。唔該，長。誒，我哋而家是發現有蒙曼靜議員，我諗時間關係或者誒何君綺都想發言。誒，或者我哋三分鐘好嗎？每人嚇唔緊要，你先講嚇，我哋盡可能安排嚇。
個環節咧，好多都係誒誒，我哋嘅年青嘅同學啦、年青人咧，係去分享佢過往喺誒即係第二語言學習嗰個，即係或者係中文學習嘅經歷啦，或者係佢一啲嘅感受。咁誒，我會睇到咧喺唔同嘅時間咧，大家學習誒呢個中文咧，其實咧面對嗰個困難。
唔同嘅嚇噉，但係有一樣嘢，我好想肯定話畀大家聽。無論我哋嘅感受係點樣咧，其實政府係非常之重視誒每一位我哋嘅即係同學誒，每一位我哋嘅年青人或者每一位我哋少數嘅族裔嘅小朋友，我哋希望誒大家都係共同一齊去建立誒美好。
好嘅香港，所以咧誒，成個教育政策對誒誒，我哋少數族裔嘅同學嘅政策目標就係希望佢哋能夠適應、盡早適應同埋融入喺學校嘅學習同埋融入社會。咁而呢個一個基本嘅條件就係我哋好希望能夠讓佢哋盡早學好中文。
咁誒過往咧，其實頭先誒大家提嘅感受或者係一啲嘅提議或者意見裏邊咧，其實離唔開咧對與中國學好中文呢一個嘅期望，究竟係誒要幾易或者要幾難？其實大家咧誒，我會聽即係或者係從呢一個成個誒對於少數族裔學習中文。
誒，如果大家有留意咧，由零四年嚟到今日咧，二零一八年咧，其實係有好多嘅誒發展嘅。零四年開始咧，就剛才有誒誒誒代表亦都講到佢誒，即係喺嗰個小一派位嗰度啦。最初係冇呢一個融合嘅政策嘅，咁而零四年開始融合嘅時，
後咧，大家又好擔心誒自己嘅小朋友會去咗一啲自己唔係咁多自己嘅誒相同族裔嘅學校，咁於是就爭取喺零八年有一啲叫做指定學校。咁而家咧經過誒幾年之後咧，大家又發覺指定學校咧雖然係可能誒感覺上係一個文化上面嘅安。
安全感，但係喺語文學習上面又唔係咁誒有利，所以咧就喺一三年嘅時候取消咗呢一個嘅誒，即係誒指定學校嘅政策，讓大家咧係可以選擇。所以頭先同學誒誒，其中有一位代表提到，而家我哋小一派位嗰張表格咧，其實我哋而家係靈活派位嘅，就唔係話誒誒。
誒，如果佢係用誒唔唔能夠接受中文誒作為教學語言咧，就一定係去嗰八間學校嗰個係另類嘅選擇。即係佢除咗係選自己校網嘅學校之外咧，佢係可以揀誒嗰八啊八間係比較誒多非華語嘅同學嘅學校。咁即係讓我哋嘅同學有多啲選擇。
咁呢個咧，當然咧，每一個選擇咧，就係關係到我哋究竟對自己中文學習嘅期望啦。我哋用咩方法喺咩環境學習最好？咁喺呢個過程裏邊咧，我哋見到政府喺咁多年嚟、十幾年嚟咧，係冇停過努力，誒誒不斷咧係同大家去溝通啦，亦都係無論係。
係誒指定學校嘅政策，還是係而家嘅誒語物第二語言嘅學習架構咧？其實都係誒聽取咗大家意見之後咧，然亦都係去徵詢誒邀請一啲專家啦、學者啦同埋大學嘅參與係去開發。咁而家頭先大家提到咧，就係喺學習支援，即係除咗學習期。
期望嗰度之外，就係就住學習支援誒各方面咧。其實誒喺課程層面咧，其實多咗。剛才提到啦，誒我哋係誒希望係大家有都提出係有系統誒有一個發展嘅階梯。咁呢個咧就係正正係而家嗰個誒第二語就語言學習架構誒畀大家。
誒就住呢一個需要咧，係去開發嘅。咁但係當然咧，呢個第二語言學習架構就唔係一路係學到去嗰個誒，即係佢個終極目標係幫助大家用小步子嘅方法，盡快去融入主流嘅。所以個目標咧都係作為一個樓梯級咧，係幫大家去融入主流。佢唔係一個終極嘅一個學習嘅誒。
阿李生，哦，多謝主席。
但係我哋每年係畀二億嘅，而家。
八個學習階，我哋叫做嚇。
間咧係一個進階式去做，但係我哋知道實行嘅時候咧。
連get go is a they would even refuse to answer questions in Chinese. Ah, no, in English.
你以後喺呢個框架之下係不會再發生嘅，唔會太淺，唔會再重複，係嘛？不會再發生。
我亦都呼籲咧，我哋誒信任老師，因為喺成個嘅即係誒教學嗰個探討或者係個誒發展嘅過程裏邊咧，其實都係有一個摸索嘅階段嘅。
誒，即係嗰個誒目標噉，所以我哋係會誒希望同學係融入喺本地嗰個主流課程，以致佢哋嘅中文學習係唔會疏蝕嘅。咁呢一個咧，呢一個當然咧，我哋知道學習中文係好艱難，所以我頭先亦都聽到咧，我哋嘅代表裏邊咧有誒講到咧，譬如就住嗰個。
教學語言嘅政策啦，或者老師嘅教學方法一啲嘅意見，噉我哋都會睇到咧，就係話無論係誒誒咩嘅誒情況底下咧，教育局咧其實都係會通過咧提供嗰個指引啦、架構啦、資源啦，而亦都係要畀學校一個專業嘅空間，同埋咧誒畀老師咧。
咧係相關嘅配套同埋培訓，咁呢啲等等咧，其實亦都係需要咧誒，我哋嘅家長啦、同學啦誒，或者成個社會咧，都有一個誒共融嘅意識，大家一齊去努力咧，先至係做得誒到嗰個效果。咁最後咧，我都想係誒，即係就住咧誒嗰個誒同，即係大家咧係亦都係講到。
教學語言嘅選擇啦，咁誒頭先我亦都喺上一節講過，誒我哋畀學校係有好清晰嘅指引，誒教學語言嘅選擇係必須根據學生嘅能力、學習需要、老師嘅能力同埋學校可以提供嘅配套措施、語言環境係去做呢一個嘅決定，亦都係應該因應。
誒咁點啊？十誒三分鐘。哦，三分鐘好，快啲快啲係啊！我首先要問問啊，副局長咧，就第一誒，我哋點樣可以幫到咧？話有老師嘅態度好差啊，嗰個言話係啊誒，think lowly of the students，因為佢哋係少數族裔。
喂喂唔得啦噉樣，呢個真係教育局有冇得幫下嘅咧？而第二個問題就係你負責課程發展嘅李生，喂嗰啲內容咁so easy，哇too repetitive，來來去去學埋咧都係我想食雪糕，我想食魚蛋咩啊？
咁點啊？係兩位唔該，局長先跟住李生，唔該，係好啊。多謝誒主席。咁咧就住老師，剛才啦都有幾位代表咧都分享過，即係誒即係老師嗰個教學嘅情況。噉我我誒我亦都係即係誒有去經常去學校去觀課嘅。其實我相信咧，我哋嘅老師。
啲咧係喺嗰個摸索個教學方法裏邊誒。剛才咧，阿議員提到咧，就係喺誒中文堂老師誒唔誒，即係拒絕用英文去回應同學嘅問題咧。咁呢個可能有時候咧喺教學上面咧，我哋誒要希望同學能夠掌握嗰種語言咧，亦都係其中一種嘅方法嚟嘅，未必一定係等於老師咧係。
係即係因為誒唔同嘅膚色或者種誒族裔唔同嘅語言去拒絕，而係可能喺教學上面有呢個需要。咁所以咧就話誒，我我覺得誒即係或者係我呢度提議咧，就係亦都係啊，我哋會加強老師嘅誒專業嘅誒誒培訓同埋認識啦，即係對就住呢個多元文化嘅教學嘅認識。但係我哋。
我頭先講依個學習架構咧，我用咗一個階段性去描繪嗰個係未足夠嘅。其實咧，我哋係應該再講埋咧係一個階梯性，即係頭先都有好多誒分享嘅時候講咧係唔progressive enough。嗱，我哋呢個學習架構咧係分。
呢個咧，其實係無論佢係第一語言或者第二語言咧，我都有呢個架構嘅存在。有咗呢個學習階梯嘅好處咧，就係老師會因應嗰個同學嘅進展咧，係決定佢係咪可以做第二階嘅嘢，做到第二階嘅嘢係唔可以做第三階嘅嘢。以往係冇呢一個噉樣。
嗱，第二個語言嘅政策方面講，我諗呢個亦都係政治現實。
保呢啲嘅差異嘅地方啦，多謝。如果冇委員反對嘅話，我哋將個會議再延長多幾分鐘，讓何君義可以發言嚇。何君義議員，緊。
嘅進階嘅情況喺度，而家我哋係有啦。咁所以咧，係嗰個大家分享過往一四年之前冇呢個學習階梯嗰個情況咧，係不一樣㗎啦。老師會根據呢一個同埋佢用一個評估工具去睇下佢究竟而家喺第一階啊、第二階啊、第三。
老師有一個具體困難咧，喺班房入邊咧，同一班可能有同學喺一屆，有同學喺二屆，有同學喺第三屆。咁呢個就係佢教學策略嗰個取捨嘅問題。不過我哋亦都知道咧，學校比較多元化去處理呢一種嘅問題，因為佢哋會用一個融入嘅模式，亦。
都會同時用一個抽離嘅模式、小組嘅模式，或者額外加課時嘅模式去處理一堆嘅問題嘅。咁所以，我哋都要相信咧，學校咧其實佢係知道個問題喺邊一度，佢只不過係用唔同嘅策略，或者一齊用不同嘅策略去處理呢個問題。即係就佢哋投訴嘅問題。
啊！呢一個我哋當然要睇學者學嗰個人，佢本身個適應啊嘅嘅方法。我用一個方法教佢，十個學生可能有啲學得好好，有啲學得冇咁理想。但係呢個就係我哋要注意個個學習差異嘅過程裏面，點樣用我哋嘅學習嘅材料啊、教學嘅策略啊去填。
主席，我好高興咧。今日咧一班年青嘅誒誒新一代係香港成長嘅少數族裔嘅朋友咧，誒反映出佢哋嘅意願。具體上我聽得明嘅就係第一，佢唔想有segregation，唔想有被分開，誒被人對待成為二等公民。
佢需要愛嘅共融integration，但係學習中文方面講，似乎喺佢哋一面全面都係咁講啦，就係誒嗰個制度、政策等等咧係唔明朗、唔清晰，同埋冇一個叫做梯階誒嘅漸進式嘅嗰種學習。而家我聽到阿李生講話有嘅。
我哋有八個階段，咁似乎呢度係喺嗰個嗰個溝通同埋個傳達方面嚟講咧，係有改善空間。我亦都知道，剛才局長話畀我哋聽，以前咧，我哋就好擔心，即係話如果係強迫少數族裔學我哋中文或者廣東話嘅時候咧，會有多少被同化嘅感覺。
有個嗰種叫做誒種族嘅嗰個敏感度喺度，但係隨住而家世界又變咗，噉佢哋又覺得，如果你要我哋去入誒EM School嘅專即係專誒誒專責嘅學校去學誒誒誒畀佢學習的話咧，又好似又未能夠融入。嗱，呢啲係矛盾咧，我覺得似乎兩。
方面咧都係有個地方可以改善，但係我覺得首先而家我就話好高興見到呢一班十九位嘅誒誒誒少少逐裔嘅新一代香港人喺度，起碼有成十幾個喺Hong Kong U讀書，喺科大讀書、嶺南讀書，全部都已經喺香港。而家呢一班就係最好嘅人才。
若果我哋有噉嘅有噉嘅intention，有噉嘅will，有心意喺度，我哋亦都有錢，我哋有政策，只不過有啲嘢要去點樣去將佢bridge over。咁呢一班人咧就係人才啦。噉啊，如果係我哋可以用佢的話，再加上話一校一社工嘅問題等等咧，將佢可。
係三月十七號咧，會將會講少數族裔嘅就業嘅問題嘅，希望大家留意下。好，咁今晚散會，唔該曬。
唔可以誒，bundle一齊，然後用用佢哋嚟train the trainer。佢哋已經係好好嘅，有譬如好似剛才誒呢位誒呢位誒誒Miss誒Diah誒Barker咧，佢嘅中文係好流暢。實際上佢佢需要嘅就係一個支援同埋一個整。
整合。如果我我哋呢一班噉嘅人才可以盡用的話咧，一定幫到我哋呢一個Scheme呢個計劃會得以推廣。當然仍然都要平衡翻少數族裔嘅嗰個誒佢嘅價值觀啊，佢哋文化嘅價值承傳嘅問題，同埋點融入係識多啲廣東話同埋中文。
學廣東話嘅時候，同時咧，即係如果識咗中文誒的話咧，誒普通話嗰個稍稍為轉轉嗰個嗰個嗰個誒個發音咧，嗰個都唔會太困難。但係最最緊要寫嗰度咧要知先。噉啊，其他嘅問題要逐步逐步去處理。噉我就提出個意見啫。多謝嚇。好啊，部長。
冇咩簡單嘅回應啊！多謝啊何何議員嘅意見。咁其實誒頭先都講咗啦，誒好強調我哋誒係共用成個政策係希望大家係共用，所以咧，剛才啊啊各位代表咧，可能有啲誒感受咧，其實誒無論你係咩感受誒，其實總整總體嚟講，我哋係。
係希望我哋成個社會係一個共融嘅社會，共同去建立一個共融嘅文化。咁而且我哋誒誒，無論係幾時咧，由零四到而家或者係以前咧，我哋都係好關心成個社會，其實都係好關心我哋嘅少數族裔。咁喺誒咁多次嘅聽證會裏邊咧，或者係過往嘅誒，即係同唔同嘅團體嘅交流都係。
可以好肯定呢樣嘢，咁所以希望我剛才嘅各位代表咧，如果誒喺個心理上，即係心裏邊感受唔係咁開心嘅，其實我好想話畀大家聽，我哋係一個共用嘅社會，或者係有啲嘅做法係有空有誒優化嘅空間，但係無論如何個總體嘅目標，我哋都係希望大家係共用一齊去建立香港。
好啊，多謝胡長。或者我加多半句咧，就係我哋其實我哋講咁多一帶一路嘅政策咧，將來我哋在座嘅各位朋友、各位同事咧，都會係有一個好大嘅資產啊！希望你哋努力嚇。噉我哋誒今晚誒唔好意思啊，我講一聲，因為我哋嘅委員會係需要就今日嘅會議咧，係延長咗時間同埋係改夜咗嘅，講一聲唔好意思。另外咧，我哋下一次開會。